Telal was the kind of city travelers described twice: once for its towers, gold in the evening light, and once for its peace, which had lasted longer than anyone alive could remember.
It sat where the desert met the trade roads, and for generations, every road had led its travelers to the same conclusion: Telal was safe. Telal was steady. Telal would still be standing long after they were gone.
At its heart ruled a King who trusted his commanders as he trusted his own sons. Completely. And, it turned out, unwisely.
He had two sons of his own. Amir, the elder, already learning the weight of a crown he would one day carry. And Malik, the younger, still young enough to think the palace halls were built for running through.
Chief among the King's commanders was Sultan Feroos: decorated, respected, and for years, utterly loyal. Or so it seemed to everyone, including the King himself.
Feroos had fought beside the King in his youth. He had been trusted with the border, then the treasury, then the palace guard itself. Every promotion looked, at the time, like a King rewarding loyalty.
The King never saw the betrayal coming, because Feroos never let him see it. That was the plan from the start, built slowly, one quiet year at a time.
On the night it happened, Feroos did not raise his own sword. He did not need to. He had already turned the men who guarded the palace gates, coin by coin, promise by promise, for longer than anyone had noticed.
By the time the alarm bells rang, they were ringing for no one. The only soldiers who answered the call were already his.
Inside the palace, Leila did not waste a single moment on disbelief. She had feared this night for longer than she had ever told her husband, and some part of her had been ready for it for years.
She went straight to her sons' rooms. Amir, the elder, old enough to understand exactly what the shouting outside meant. And Malik, the younger, old enough to be frightened, too young to be told everything.
"We are leaving. Now. No questions yet," she told them, and something in her voice made even Amir stop asking why.
Malik reached for his mother's hand without being told to. Amir reached for the door, already scanning the corridor the way he had seen the guards do a hundred times, without ever expecting to need it himself.
They left through a passage no map of Telal ever showed: a narrow servants' route built for exactly this kind of night, generations before, by a King who had once feared exactly this kind of man and never told anyone why.
Behind them, the palace towers caught the fire meant for the throne room. Smoke climbed higher than any tower Telal had ever built.
By morning, Sultan Feroos stood where the King once stood, and told the people of Telal that peace had been restored, and that nothing needed to change.
Almost nothing had changed, in the streets, in the markets, in the calls to prayer. Only the family at the very top of it all was gone, and already being spoken of as if they never existed.
Leila did not look back at the burning towers. Not because she didn't want to. Because she couldn't afford to; not with two sons and no guards and a very long walk ahead of her.
By dawn, the three of them were specks in an empty desert, walking away from the only home Amir and Malik had ever known, toward nothing they could yet see.
Amir walked in front, watching the horizon the way a soldier would, even though no one had trained him to. Malik walked beside his mother, too tired to be afraid anymore, simply putting one foot after the other.
Leila carried little that night: a change of clothes, some water, and one small clay vial, wrapped carefully, that she never let out of her sight, not even to sleep.
She had not told her sons what it was. Not yet. That would come later, in the quiet of the desert, when Malik was old enough to be trusted with it, and the two of them were far enough from Telal that a whisper couldn't reach the wrong ears.
For now, there was only the walking, the silence between them, and the city behind them, already learning to answer to a different name.
None of them knew yet what the desert still held for them: a vial with a purpose Leila alone understood, and, somewhere ahead, a seer who would look at Malik and see something none of them had dared to say out loud.
This is where Warrior of the Sand Dunes begins.
Original fiction. Not history. Not folklore. A new story, from the sands.